{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Compute \\(\\lim_{x \\to 3}\\frac{x^4-81}{2x^2-5x-3}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>53/12</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>108/7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Limit does not exist</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>108/7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302835/gate2019-cs-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let X be a square matrix. Consider the following two statements on X.<br><br>\nI. X is invertible<br>\nII. Determinant of X is non-zero <br><br>\nWhich one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I implies II; II does not imply I</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II implies I; I does not imply II</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I does not imply II; II does not imply I</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I and II are equivalent statements</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I and II are equivalent statements</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302839/gate2019-cs-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The domain of the function \\(\\log (\\log \\sin (x))\\) is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(0\\lt x \\lt \\pi\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(2 n \\pi \\lt x \\lt (2 n+1) \\pi\\), for n in N</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Empty set</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Empty set</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213573/isro2018-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Consider a matrix P whose only eigenvectors are the multiples of \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1\\\\ 4 \\end{bmatrix}\\). <br>\nConsider the following statements. <br>\n(I) P does not have an inverse <br>\n(II) P has a repeated eigenvalue <br>\n(III) P cannot be diagonalized <br>\nWhich one of the following options is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Only I and III are necessarily true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Only II is necessarily true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only I and II are necessarily true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only II and III are necessarily true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Only II and III are necessarily true</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204100/gate2018-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider a matrix \\(A=uv^{T}\\; where \\; u=\\begin{bmatrix} 1\\\\ 2 \\end{bmatrix},v=\\begin{bmatrix} 1\\\\ 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\)  Note that \\(v^{T}\\)  denotes the transpose of v. The largest eigenvalue of A is _____. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "3",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204091/gate2018-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The value of \\(\\int_{0}^{\\frac{\\pi }{4}}x\\cos (x^{2})dx\\) correct to three decimal places\n(assuming that \\(\\pi\\)  = 3.14 ) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.27",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204090/gate2018-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following is a closed form expression for the generating function of the sequence \\(\\left \\{ a_{n} \\right \\}\\), where \\(a_{n}=2n+3\\) for all n = 0, 1, 2,...? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{3}{(1-x)^{2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{3x}{(1-x)^{2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{2-x}{(1-x)^{2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{3-x}{(1-x)^{2}}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{3-x}{(1-x)^{2}}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204075/gate2018-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Using Newton-Raphson method, a root correct to 3 decimal places of  \\(x^{3}-3 x-5=0\\) <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>2.222</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2.275</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2.279</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2.279</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128599/isro2017-3\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>If A is a skew symmetric matrix then \\(A^{t}\\)  is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Diagonal matrix</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-A</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>-A</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/128505/isro2017-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>If the characteristics polynomial of 3x3 matrix M over R ( the set of real numbers) is\n\\(\\lambda ^{3}-4\\lambda ^{2}+a\\lambda +30,a\\in R\\), and one eigenvalue of M is 2, then the largest among the absolute values of the eigenvalues of M is ________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118618/gate2017-2-52#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>If a random variable X has a Poisson distribution with mean 5, then the expectation \\(E[(X+2)^{2}]\\) equals ______________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "54",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118513/gate2017-2-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider a quadratic equation \\(x^{2} -13x +36 = 0\\) with coefficients in a base b. The solutions of this equation in the same base b are x = 5 and x = 6. Then b = ___________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "8",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118185/gate2017-2-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(P=\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp; 1&amp;-1 \\\\ 2&amp;-3 &amp; 4\\\\ 3 &amp;-2 &amp; 3 \\end{bmatrix} \\) and \\( Q=\\begin{bmatrix} -1 &amp; -2&amp;-1 \\\\ 6 &amp; 12&amp; 6\\\\ 5&amp;10 &amp; 5 \\end{bmatrix}\\) be two matrices.\nThen the rank of P +Q is _____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "2",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118363/gate2017-2-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>If \\(f(x)=R sin(\\frac{\\pi x}{2})+S,f'(\\frac{1}{2})=\\sqrt{2}\\) and \\( \\int_{0}^{1}f(x)dx=\\frac{2R}{\\pi }\\), then the constants R and S are, respectively <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\) and \\( \\frac{16}{\\pi}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\) and 0</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{\\pi}\\) and 0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{\\pi}\\) and \\( \\frac{16}{\\pi}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{4}{\\pi}\\) and 0</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118262/gate2017-2-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let A be nxn real valued square symmetric matrix of rank 2 with \\(\\sum_{i=1}^{n}\\sum_{j=1}^{n}A^{2}_{ij}=50\\). Consider\nthe following statements. <br> <br>(I) One eigen value must be in [-5, 5]   <br>      (II) The eigen value with the largest magnitude must be strictly greater than 5. <br> <br>\nWhich of the above statements about eigen values of A is/are necessarily CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (I) and (II)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(I) only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(II) only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Neither (I) nor (II)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>(I) only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118312/gate2017-1-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}